Ilham Rinaldi

Business & Operation | Data Science Enthusiast

Jakarta, Indonesia | +62895325738473 | ilhamrinaldee@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/ilhamrinaldi

Summary

With over 8+ years of leadership experience in managing events, divisions, and organizations, driving team performance and operational excellence. Graduated as a Business Management Bachelor. Developed, monitored, and analyzed a comprehensive farmers' database and dashboard. Created and implemented Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs) across all main business functions, and developed internal tools that optimized manufacturing processes, stock flow, and bookkeeping, resulting in over 3+ billion IDR in recorded finished goods. Using data science tools, Python, SQL, Matplotlib, Tableau, and Google Workspace, brings strong technical skills. Passionate to contribute data science teams through expertise in statistical modeling, machine learning, and predictive analytics.

Professional Experiences

PT. Elevasi Agri Indonesia (Elevarm)

May 2023 - present

Upstream Operation Lead

- Created standard procedures for all of Elevarm's main business focuses.
- Monitored Yarnen (financing program) projects, averaging 650 million rupiah per month.
- Provided profitability reports for the partnership cultivation program, covering over 1+ billion rupiah
- Developed internal tools to manage manufacturing processes, stock flow, and bookkeeping, resulting in 3+ billion rupiah in finished goods recorded.
- Created Yarnen scoring as a KYC (Know Your Customer) tool for curating potential key farmers based on land size, crop risk, and financial background, reducing overdue projects by 40% by 2024 and managing 1.8+ billion rupiah in project value since Q4 2023.
- Led a team of seven, including one procurement specialist, one upstream operation staff member, and five operational admins, and directly reported to the CTO (Chief Technology Officer).

PT. Elevasi Agri Indonesia (Elevarm)

June 2022 - May 2023

Business Development

- Developed the farmer journey and created the funnel stage, covering data for over 10,000 farmers.
- Piloted and developed the Yarnen program, now one of the main business focuses, covering over 2,500 key farmers with 8.2 billion rupiah in GMV (Gross Merchandise Value).
- Analyzed the agribusiness model for 89 commodities based on industry best practices and literature reviews.
- Analyzed all branch operational issues and reported them to management weekly.
- Promoted the Elevarm program to key farmers across West Java, Central Java, and DI Yogyakarta to open market opportunities and directly reported to the CAO (Chief Agriculture Officer).

PT. Neura Cipta Nusantara (Neurafarm)

May 2021 - May 2022

Business Development

- Experimented with new business models, including trading, financing, and partnership programs.
- Increased direct sales of KYS (Know Your Soil) products, doubling sales in three months.
- Piloted and developed a trading business, covering three B2B partners with over 350 million rupiah in GMV during a three-month incubation period.
- Piloted and developed an agri-inputs consignment model, covering 45 agri-inputs stores with over 550 million rupiah in GMV during a six-month incubation period.
- First full-time employee of the company, directly reported to the Chief Executive Officer.

Perum Jasa Tirta II Aug 2020 - Feb 2021

Business Development

- Learned ISO 31000, Risk Management.
- Learned the Malcolm Baldrige scoring model.
- Learned the KPKU scoring model for state-owned enterprises.
- Created 10 socialized videos about internal good corporate governance and risk management.
- Mentored directly by a Risk Manager with over 15 years of expertise in risk management.

Garfaria Sep 2018 - Dec 2020

Chief Executive Officer (founder)

- Led a team of four, including a researcher, operations staff, technician, and designer
- Received funding from the Ministry of Education and Culture, Republic of Indonesia, totalling 20 million rupiah.
- Developed an automated hydroponic system for 1,000 plant sites

Education

Dibimbing.id Nov 2024 - Current

Data Science

• Learn about data data preparation, science modelling, data visualization

Technical Skills: Python, Matplotlib, Tableau

Sepuluh Nopember Institute of Technology

Sep 2017 - Apr 2021

Bachelor of Business Management | GPA: 3.41

Thesis: Maturity Level Risk Management in State-Owned Enterprises (Case Study: Perum Jasa Tirta II)

Relevant Coursework: Business Statistics, New Venture Creation

Volunteer/Organizational Experience:

- COO for Business Management Student Association (BMSA) 2019, led five divisions, and organized 15+ events.
- Project Leader for ITS Night Markets (PAMMITS) 2019, attracted over 8,000 visitors per day.
- Obtained Advanced Leadership Training Certification ITS (LKMM-TM).
- Member of Leadership Mentor ITS (PP LKMM), mentored over seven departments at ITS.
- Advisor for Business Management Festival 2019, attracted over 15,000 visitors.

Skills

Language : Indonesia (native), English (professional working proficiency)

Software : Python, Google Workspace, Power BI

Soft Skill : Problem solving, Teamwork, Multi-tasking ability, Analytical Thinking, Leadership, Flexibility Hard Skill : Data cleaning & preparation, Data visualization & dashboarding, Data analysis & modelling

Certification / Awards

- Data Literacy Certificate by Datacamp (2024)
- Python Basic Certificate by HackerRank (2024)
- Top 5 in the National Student Competition for Business, Management, and Finance (KBMK) held by the Ministry of Education and Culture, Republic of Indonesia (2020).
- Top 5 in the National Business Plan Competition held by Islamic University of Indonesia (2020).
- Finalist in EURECA Prasetiya Mulya for Marketing Plan Competition (2019).
- Finalist business model in Kompetisi Bisnis Mahasiswa Indonesia (KBMI) East Java Region (2018).

Projects